Now that we have discussed deadlocks,
let's look at a classic problem that,
if not properly handled, can lead to deadlocks.
I'm calling this the chopstick-variation of the
dining philosophers' problem; the original
problem has been introduced by Dijkstra.
Suppose we have n philosophers (they
represent our threads) and n chopsticks.
Each philosopher would like to eat, but to do
so he/she needs 2 chopsticks, the one on their
left side and the one on their right side.
Once a philosopher gets both chopsticks,
others of course cannot use the same
chopsticks used by the philosopher.
If you reflect about it, you will see that if we
have 2 philosophers only one can eat at a time,
if we have 3 philosophers only 1 can
eat at a time, if we have 4 philosophers
than 2 can eat in parallel (but they
cannot be adjacent ones), and so on.
So, can this setup lead to deadlock
if our algorithm is poorly designed?
Let's have a look and let us
consider the following solution,
which we call pick-left-and-then-pick-right.
The first thing we have to do is to
check if the mutual exclusion property is
satisfied or not. I leave this
to you as a homework (again,
reason formally about whether the
property is satisfied or not).
The second thing we want to check
is whether deadlocks can occur.
From our previous discussion, if
mutual exclusion, hold and wait,
no preemption and circular wait can happen
simultanously, then deadlocks can occur.
Hopefully, you have found out that
mutual exclusion is satisfied.
Do we have hold and wait? Yes, if a
philosopher manages to get the left chopstick,
then the philosopher will not release it until
he/she manages to get the right chopstick too.
Do we have no preemption? Yes, 2
chopsticks are released by the same
philosopher that manages to get them once the
philosopher completes its critical section.
Do we have circular waits?
Indeed, as shown in this slide.
Hence, this solution is not
valid, it can lead to a deadlock.
In this slide the arrow from
the philosopher to the chopstick
means the philosopher is waiting for the
chopstick. The arrow from the chopstick
to the philosopher means the
philosopher got the chopstick.